Guide to the Frances Patai Audio Collection ALBA.AUDIO.131
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Frances Patai Audio Collection
1985-1992
ALBA.AUDIO.131
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
0.5 linear feet (36 audiocassettes)
Frances Patai was an educator, writer, historian and feminist activist. Born in New York in 1930, she earned her bachelor's and master's degrees at the City College of New York in the 1950s and taught English and Communication courses throughout the City University of New York (CUNY) system. Patai was deeply concerned with human rights issues, in particular the rights and status of women, and in the last decade of her life she devoted her efforts to researching and writing a book on U.S. women medical personnel who volunteered during the Spanish Civil War. The oral histories that make up this collection are part of her extensive research material. The collection consists of interviews with volunteers from the Spanish Civil War, primarily the women who served as nurses.
Patai, Frances
Historical/Biographical Note
Frances Patai was born on New York City's Lower East Side in 1930. As a teenager, she performed in Jewish resorts in the Catskills as an actress and dancer. In her twenties she attended classes at the City College of New York, earning her bachelor's degree in 1955 and her MA in 1957. Beginning in the 1970s she served as an English and Communications instructor at various institutions in the City University of New York (CUNY) system, including long-term appointments at John Jay College and the Borough of Manhattan Community Colleges.
Throughout her career Patai was concerned with the rights and status of women, addressing in a series of essays and articles issues related to rape, pornography, and abuse. During the 1980s she worked with the feminist organization Woman against Pornography, serving as spokesperson and organizing their annual WAP Awards, an event that promoted the non-sexist representation of women in advertising. In later life Patai turned her attention to the anti-fascist movements of the 1930s, and began to investigate the history of American volunteers who joined the Republican forces to fight against Franco's army during the Spanish Civil War. Patai focused her attention on the participation of American women volunteers in the Spanish Civil War, devoting her efforts to researching and writing a book on the contributions of nurses. Through her friendship with Fredericka Martin -- a nurse with the Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy who collected extensive biographical material on her former colleagues -- Patai gained access to unique primary materials, and to the surviving nurses themselves. She conducted these interviews over several years, as part of her research project.
Patai died in 1998 before she could bring her project to fruition. She was 67 years old.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Fredericka Martin Papers (ALBA 001) Julia Newman: "Into the Fire" Research Files (ALBA 226) Frances Patai Papers (ALBA 131) Frances Patai Photographs (ALBA PHOTO 131) Frances Patai File in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archive (ALBA) Vertical Files: Individuals (ALBA VF 2)
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of 36 audiocassettes, which were separated from the Francis Patai Papers (ALBA 131). The interviews were conducted by Patai in the period 1985 to 1992, in the course of research for her book project on U.S. women medical personnel who vounteered during the Spanish Civil War. Most are with the women who volunteered as nurses, but also included are interviews with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veterans Moe Fishman and Steve Nelson, and with Marion Wachtel, widow of ALB volunteer Robert Merriman. Drafts of Patai's planned book, and her article "Heroines of the Good Fight: Testimonies of U.S. Volunteer Nurses in the Spanish Civil War, 1936-1939" ( Nursing History Review, 3 (1995): 79-104), which utilizes the interviews in this collection, can be found in the Patai Papers (ALBA 131). Also included in the collection are tapes of a conference and a veterans' dinner, and a recording of Spanish Civil War songs.
Arrangement
Each recording has been assigned a unique item number (e.g., ALBA A 131-001), and the collection is arranged in alphabetical order by last name of the interviewee. (Women's maiden names, or names used during service in Spain, are listed first -- followed by names used later in life.)
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Researcher is responsible for the cost of creating an access copy of any item.
For details E-mail: gail.malmgreen@nyu.edu
Abraham Lincoln Brigade.; Martin, Fredericka I.; Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy.; Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy.; Patai, Frances; Americans |z Spain |x History |y 20th century.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Personal narratives.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Participation, American |v Interviews.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Women.
- Bell (Roberts), Hilda, Jan 15, 1991 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-001)
- Bell (Roberts), Hilda; Mildred Rackley (Simon), Jan 14, 1991 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-002)
- Davidow, Ruth, Jan 20, 1992 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-003)
- Fisher, Ruth and Harry, May 21, 1988 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-007)
- Fishman, Moe (Moses), Nov 6, 1989 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-008)
- Freeman (Feinberg), Helen, Apr 20, 1990 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-006)
- Goldin (Spiegel), Irene; Esther Brown, Jan 22, 1991 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-034)
- Gonzala, Garcia Delgado, Jul 15, 1988 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-009)
- Hill (Klein), Josephine, Apr 23, 1990 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-013)
- Hill (Klein), Josephine, Apr 23, 1990 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-014)
- Klavantz, Rae, Jul 1991 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-015)
- Leight, Clara, Dec 17, 1986 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-016)
- Leight, Clara, Dec 17, 1986 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-017)
- Levine (Hartzman), May, Jan 27, 1991 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-018)
- Malbin, Virginia, 1985 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-019)
- Malbin, Virginia, Jan 25, 1991 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-021)
- Malbin, Virginia; Esther Silverstein (Blanc), Jan 25, 1991 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-020)
- Martin, Fredericka, undated (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-022)
- Martin, Fredericka, Oct 8, 1989 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-023)
- Merriman (Wachtel), Marion, Feb 3, 1991 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-024)
- Nelson, Steve, Apr 19, 1991 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-025)
- Nelson, Steve, Apr 19, 1991 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-026)
- North (Green), Helen; Spanish Civil War Songs, May 8, 1987 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-010)
- Rackley (Simon), Mildred, Jan 14, 1991 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-032)
- Rolfe, Mary, Jan 18, 1991 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-027)
- Seborer (Greenspan), Celia, Feb 21, 1987 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-011)
- Seborer (Greenspan), Celia, May 15, 1992 (Drawer 4, Carton 131-012)
- Sendor, Andrea (Sister Benedicta), May 15, 1990 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-028)
- Schulman (Durem), Rebecca, Jan 26, 1991 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-004)
- Schulman (Durem), Rebecca; Helen Freeman (Feinberg), Jan 27, 1991 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-005)
- Shuldiner (Goldman), Anne, May 22, 1990 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-029)
- Silverstien (Blanc), Esther; Sana Goldblatt, Jan 17, 1991 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-030)
- Silverstein (Blanc), Esther; Mary Rolfe, Jan 18, 1991 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-031)
- Temple, Lenora, Dec 13, 1986 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-035)
- Spanish Civil War Conference, Mar 19, 1988 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-033)
- VALB: 55th Anniversary Dinner, Apr 26, 1992 (Drawer 4, Cassette 131-036)